Hello friends, today I am here to
share some information about the double K stand. The
DJ stand or double K stand is a
plastic tube of about 26 cm.
It is a completely flexible tube, as
you can see. This
stand is used in urology operations,
and many patients have many
questions related to it, as to why this DJ
stand is being inserted, and it is
used
inside our body. So, there is a lot of anxiety
among people as to why it is being
inserted in our body.
We will discuss all these things today.
[Music] It is
in the urinary bladder, that is, in our urinary
bladder. So, this first one works to
anchor the stand in the kidney,
as if it remains there, it does this. The
second one is
in the urinary bladder. To prevent this stand from getting displaced, there are
two of them, it is
made of very soft material. If this stand is
inside our body, then generally there are no
problems or many symptoms,
and even while living with it, we can continue our
normal life.  All routine tasks can be performed.
It is an integral part of all normal stone surgeries, such as PCL, URSL, and all stone operations.
Generally,
if someone has kidney stone disease or
ureteric stone disease, there is swelling.
Nowadays, lasers are
used extensively, so sometimes the stones are
converted into very small powders.
After that, it becomes almost necessary to have this stand.
Because of the stand,
all the particles that we have created with the laser
are removed from the body with the help of the stand. Along with this,
swelling of the kidney also
reduces due to the stand.
Because of this stand, all the urine from the
kidney can drain well from inside the stand as well as from the sides of the stand. So
this is the purpose of this tent. It
comes in different sizes. If the children
are small, it also comes in sizes of 16 cm or 20 cm. There are
many major surgeries
like reconstructive surgery.  Urology
kidney transplant operations take place.
Surgery is done for large ureters.
We make flaps etc. in which the urinary
tract has become small at some point. We
make a flap of the bladder for it or we are
planting the rim of the ureter for any reason. In all
such surgeries,
this stand is definitely inserted. Its
purpose is to prevent urine leakage. This
means that in such a big
surgery, stitches have been done in the unit track, so
this stand is inserted to prevent urine leakage from anywhere.
Due to the stand, a
streamlined urine flow is maintained
and urine does not go out of the unit track.
This is its purpose. Sometimes
in acute situations, like the patient is suffering from stone and has
high grade fever and infection,
if the stone operation is done
directly at that time, then there is a
risk of the infection spreading throughout the body.
In such cases, this stand is inserted first.
This is a very minimal
part of the surgery. This
stand is inserted in the unit track in hardly 5-10 minutes.  It goes away.
Sometimes, we can even perform this procedure locally in women. By
inserting such a stent, the blocked flow of urine in the
kidney starts functioning smoothly again.
Any kidney
infection or pus gets drained out. The
patient stops having fever. When the patient
recovers completely due to this stent, in about a week or 10 days,
then we are able to conduct stone surgery very safely. So,
one of the main purposes of this stent
is drainage of obstruction. Drainage
of infection means that
if there is an infection or blockage in the urine tract of the kidney anywhere in the body, then
its
drainage is a part of any major surgery. Be it
stone surgery,
recall-specific surgery, kidney
transplant surgery, in such major
surgeries, this stent is included in our rate.
Now you will ask what are the symptoms of a stent
or what are the costs associated with it,
what are the complications?
Due to the presence of stent, sometimes blood can appear in the urine.
Due to this, urine is obstructed.  There may be a desire to go again and again,
due to this there may be some
pain while passing urine, so this is a
common symptom, but such
symptoms occur in very few patients and even
if they occur, they can be controlled with simple pain relievers
and simple medicines,
so there is no need to worry about the stent,
generally in most of the cases this
stent is temporary, in 2 to 3 weeks the
stent can be taken out or removed from the body through local CG
and it does
not cause any harm to the body, so this was the
information about stent, Hello